So at some point in their lives, nearly everybody has wanted to dig a hole
down to the center of the earth. The only problem is nobody
ever has actually dug a hole down that far. This leads us to the
question that this video is all about. If humanity decided that digging
a hole was the number one objective of our species, then how
deep down could we actually dig with modern day technology?
Lets say that we start somewhere on the earths surface and just start digging from
there. Not too far down, at 1.8 meters, and we arrive
at the standard grave depth in western culture. So if youre afraid of
zombies, this is how far down theyll be coming from. 4 meters
down and we arrive at the depth that pharaoh tutankhamuns tomb was discovered.
At. A little further, at 6 meters below the surface, weve reached the maximum
depth that metal detectors can pick up signals from. At 12
meters we can find the deepest burrows dug by animals,
the Nile crocodile. A little further down, at 20 meters
and we arrive at the depth of the Paris catacombs beneath the city of Paris.
A tomb that holds the remains of over 6 million people.
Double that distance to 40 meters down and we can see the deepest
swimming pool in the world. If you drained this pool and jumped into
it from the top, it would take nearly 3 seconds before you
would hit the bottom. 100 meters down is the usual distance that
governments bury their nuclear waste at. And just beneath that,
at 105.5 meters down, is the deepest metro station in the
world, located in Kiev. Moving on to 122
meters down and we see the deepest known point that a plants roots have
ever reached. A fig tree in South Africa.
220 meters down and we arrive at the deepest river in the world,
the Congo river in Africa. Beyond that, at 240
meters, you can ride through the deepest railway tunnel in the world that connects
the japanese islands of Honshu and Hokkaido. But at 287
meters down, you can drive through the deepest road tunnel in the world.
In Norway, 305 meters down and you would still be
vulnerable to the B 82 earth penetrating nuclear warhead,
which can destroy structures up to this depth beneath the surface.
Incredibly though, at 392 meters, we arrive at the deepest well
and possibly deepest hole ever dug by hand. This is
the Woodingdene water well in the UK, and it was dug all the
way back in 1862. At 603
meters down, we arrive at something, the deepest vertical
drop inside of a cave. If you were unfortunate enough to
be in this cave and fall down this hole, the fall would be higher up
than falling. From the top of the one World Trade center in New York,
and the fall would take you over 11 seconds before hitting
the bottom. Even further down though at 700 meters is where the
chilean miners were trapped at for 69 days back in 2010.
970 meters down is the deepest hole ever dug
that still has an open sky above it. The Bingham Canyon
open pit mine in Utah. This pit is so deep that
you could place the tallest building in the entire world in the center
and still have over 100 more meters to the surface.
Much further down at 19 10 meters though,
is where the deepest concert ever held happened by the band Agonizer
in Finland. 1640 2 meters
down is the depth of the deepest lake on Earth,
Lake Baikal in Russia. And 1857
meters down is the deepest part of the Grand Canyon. The deepest
known cave on earth is located 2197
meters beneath the surface in Georgia. But the deepest hole
that you could actually fall into goes way deeper
than even this. All the way down at 3132
meters is the bottom of the Moab Khatsong mineshaft in
South Africa. Taking the elevator takes four and a half minutes to
reach the bottom. But if you fell into it from the top it would take
you 25 entire seconds for you to hit the bottom
and think about what you've just done long enough to receive
and miss an entire phone call. Even further down
at 3600 meters is the deepest point that a multicellular
organism has been found alive, this freaky looking worm.
But human beings themselves have been even deeper than this.
4000 meters down is the deepest part of the
deepest mine on Earth, also located in South Africa.
The trip from the surface down to the bottom takes over an hour to complete
and the temperature at the bottom can reach a sweltering 66
degrees celsius. 6000 meters is the average
depth of the oceanic crust beneath the ocean floor.
Way down at 8848 meters is
the height of Mount Everest if it were placed underground instead.
10,994 meters down
is the bottom of the Marianas trench which is the deepest part
of the ocean. I already covered the depth of the ocean in another
video, but unbelievably humans have actually dug down significantly
deeper than even this. For reference about whats next 11,887
meters is the average altitude that a commercial airliner flies
at. But deeper than that at 12,262
meters is the depth of the Kola superdeep borehole,
a project where the Soviet Union attempted to drill all the way through the
earths crust. They only reached a third of the way there though because the
temperature at this depth reached 180 degrees celsius
which was too hot for the drill to continue operating any further.
The hole is also only 23 cm wide
so luckily you cant accidentally fall into it. If you
dropped a quarter down the shaft though, it would take about 50 seconds
before it hit the bottom. Recently however, this depth has
been surpassed by the Z 44 Chavio oil and gas well
which has drilled down to a depth of 12,376
meters. Thats the equivalent of stacking 15 burj khalifas
on top of each other and currently represents the deepest hole that
humanity has ever dug. The crust however can extend
down to 70,000 meters below the earths surface and the
planets center is located 6371
km down. If the surface of the earth is Lisbon,
Portugal and the planets center is Astana, Kazakhstan then
humanity so far has just ventured this tiny,
insignificant distance. If you enjoyed the video that you
just watched then I hope that you'll subscribe to my channel here. And don't forget
to hit the bell for updated videos. You can visit my Patreon by
clicking here if you'd like to directly support the channel and vote on future video
topics. And I hope to see you next Friday for another new video.
Then.